{"tossups": [{"question": "<b>An unsuccessful siege of the Jasna Gora Monastery during this conflict stiffened resistance by one side, which formed the Confederation of Tyszowce. Janusz Radziwill</b> <b>switched sides in this conflict by signing the Union of (+)</b> <b>Kedainiai. This conflict was</b> <b>ended by the Peace of Oliva and the Truce of Andrusovo and began with an uprising of Zaphorozian Cossacks which cost one side control of Ukraine, the (*)</b> Khmelnytsky Uprising. Hetman Stefan Czarniecki helped John Casimir II drive out the invading armies of Alexis I and Charles X in this conflict. For the points, name this devastating Russian and Swedish invasion which broke the power of Poland-Lithuania.", "answer": "The<b> Deluge</b> (accept the<b> Swedish Deluge</b> or the<b> Russian Deluge</b>, accept<b> First</b> or <b>Second Northern War</b>, prompt on <b>Northern Wars</b>, prompt on<b> Russo-Polish War</b>, prompt on <b>Swedish-Polish War</b>, do not accept or prompt on<b> Great Northern War</b>)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "<b>In a speech delivered in this city, William Seward remarked that the incompatibility of slave states and free states presented an \u201cirrepressible conflict,\u201d which could lead to civil</b> <b>war. One of the final stops on the Underground Railroad was in this city\u2019s (+)</b> <b>Kelsey</b> <b>Landing, located along the Genesee River. Met with controversy due to her sex, Abigail Post was elected as the presiding officer of a convention in this city, where the (*)</b><em> Declaration</em> <em>of Sentiments</em> was approved two weeks after its introduction at the Seneca Falls Convention. Justice Ward Hunt fined a woman one hundred dollars for casting a vote in this city. For the points, name this city in New York, the birthplace of Susan B. Anthony.", "answer": "<b> Rochester</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "<b>Jan Dismas Zelenka spent the majority of his career in this city, where he controversially replaced Johann David Heinichen as Kapellmeister. J.S. Bach\u2019s</b><em><b> Mass in B Minor</b></em><b> was sourced from one of his Kyrie-Gloria masses that was named for the court of this city where</b> <b>he worked under (+)</b> <b>Frederick Augustus. The score to</b><em><b> Five Days, Five Nights</b></em><b>, a film set</b> <b>in this city, was written by Dmitri Shostakovich in this city, where he also wrote his eighth string quartet. A five-note rising motif is referred to as this city\u2019s (*)</b> \u201cAmen\u201d. For the points, name this German city, the site of a Allied bombing campaign in 1945.", "answer": "<b> Dresden</b>", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Auditory Fine Arts"}, {"question": "<b>A kingdom named for this region sent the emissary Heliodorus to build a pillar in honor of the god Vasudeva as a gift to Bhagabhadra of the Sunga dynasty. Darius I deported the people of Barca in Cyrenaica here in the 5th century BCE. This region once ruled by the rebellious satrap (+) Bessus was home to a prominent Greek population after its conquest by Alexander. This region names the last wild species of (*)</b> camel in the world. For the points, name this historic region in Central Asia east of Sogdiana that was the site of a Greek kingdom ruled by Diodotus I.", "answer": "<b> Bactria</b> (accept<b> Avestan</b>)", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {}, {"question": "<b>The credit rating agency Dun and Bradstreet is a descendant of the Mercantile Agency, founded by this family. One member of this family founded the</b><em><b> New York Journal of</b></em> <em><b>Commerce</b></em><b> with (+)</b> <b>Samuel Morse and faced a series of namesake riots in 1834. This</b> <b>Congregationalist family believed in a \u201cCopper skinned\u201d America where people could intermarry. A member of this family arranged for Yale students to teach slaves on the (*) </b>Amistad English and told Charles Sumner that African Americans could only have rights when they had a \u201cmusket in one hand and a ballot in the other\u201d. For the points, what family of New York abolitionists included brothers Lewis and Arthur?", "answer": "<b> Tappan</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b>A ruler of this dynasty fought against Mansingh Tomar and founded the city of Agra. That ruler from this dynasty succeeded his father Bahlul, who founded this dynasty after</b> <b>the abdication of the last (+)</b> <b>Sayyid ruler Alam Shah. One ruler from this dynasty lost a</b> <b>battle in which their opponent used 700 carts tied together with ropes as well as firearms and field artillery. This dynasty\u2019s last ruler (*) </b> Ibrahim was killed in that battle against Babur, the First Battle of Panipat. For the points, name this last ruling dynasty of the Delhi Sultanate.", "answer": "<b> Lodi</b> Dynasty", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "<b>A 1640 volcanic eruption may have persuaded these people to sign a peace treaty at the Parliament of Quillin. News of an ambush at Curalaba prompted these people to launch an uprising that culminated in the Destruction of the Seven Cities. According to the Spanish</b> <b>chronicler (+)</b> <b>Diego de Rosales, these people encountered Incan expeditions around the</b> <b>Bio-Bio River and later defeated the conquistador Pedro de Valdivia. These people lost their home territories after the Pacification of (*) </b> Araucania during the 1800s. For the points, name these indigenous people who still inhabit southern Argentina and Chile today.", "answer": "<b> Mapuche</b> [or<b> Araucanian</b>s before mention]", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "<b>An electrician named Platyev claimed to have hit the perpetrator of this event in the face by throwing a screwdriver. An order to replace Filipp Medved was countermanded by the central person in this event, who may or may not have been targeted by Vania</b> <b>(+)</b> <b>Zaporozhets. Vasili Ulrikh secretly tried the perpetrator of this event, who was given</b> <b>Zaporozhets. Vasili Ulrikh secretly tried the perpetrator of this event, who was given</b> <b>a Nagant revolver and allowed to walk into the (*)</b> <b>a Nagant revolver and allowed to walk into the (*)</b> Smolny Institute. The NKVD might have ordered Leonid Nikolayev to perpetrate this event. Stalin\u2019s pretext for his first Great Purge was, for the points, what event, the 1934 killing of the Leningrad Party Boss?", "answer": "<b> Assassination</b> of Sergey<b> Kirov</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "<b>As chairman of the Senate Small Business Committee, this man created Small Business Development Centers in universities. Congressional hearings over the combined oral (+) contraceptive pill were named for this man, who was the only senator along with Thomas Eagleton and William Hathaway opposed Gerald Ford\u2019s vice presidency. The 1969 (*)</b> Santa Barbara Oil Blowout inspired this man to hold a teach-in on an annual event he founded. This counselor of The Wilderness Society was praised by Vince Lombardi as \u201cthe nation\u2019s #1 conservationist\u201d at Oshkosh. For the points, name this Wisconsin Democrat who created Earth Day.", "answer": "Gaylord<b> Nelson</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b>Residents of this city have partially re-appropriated a derogatory term for them, Jafa. This city\u2019s SkyCity Casino is home to the tallest freestanding structure in the (+) southern hemisphere, the Sky Tower. One nickname for this city, Sail City, is explained by its double harbors, Manukau and Waitemata. Named for George (*)</b> Eden, patron of William Hobson, this city is also called Tamaki by its Polynesian population, which is the world\u2019s largest by most measures. For the points, name this city located on a namesake isthmus of North Island, the most populous in New Zealand.", "answer": "<b> Auckland</b>", "metadata": "Geography - Geography"}, {}, {}, {"question": "<b>The Doolittle Committee investigated issues at one location in this event, which ended with a \u201cdeeply impressed\u201d William Tecumseh Sherman and an \u201cappalled\u201d Samuel Tappan.</b> <b>Fighting that led to this event included the scalping of (+)</b> <b>Narbona and Manuelito and</b> <b>Barboncito\u2019s raid on Fort Defiance. The round up for this event was called for by James Carleton and carried out by (*) </b> Kit Carson. Ute scourts slaved many people in this event. An interment camp created in this event suffered a flood from the Pecos River and faced Comanche raids, leading to that camp\u2019s inhabitants stealing voer 1000 horses back. This event ended at Fort Sumner in Bosque Redondo. For the points, name this 1864 forced march of the Navajo.", "answer": "The<b> Long Walk</b> of the Navajo to Bosque Redondo", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b>The Arellano Felix brothers, this man\u2019s nephews, gained access to a \u201cplaza\u201d in Sonora.</b> <b>Diego Enrique Osorno contacted this man in (+)</b> <b>prison, revealing much of his life. In</b> <b>2014, this man was transferred away from the Altiplano Prison. This man took power after Pedro Avil\u00b4es was killed and this man had DEA agent Kiki Camarena tortured with a power drill, leading to the U.S. intervening in Operation Layenda. This man was known as (*)</b> El Padrino, or \u201cthe Godfather.\u201d For the points, name this Guadalajara Cartel drug trafficker, the father of modern drug trafficking through Mexico.", "answer": "Miguel \u00b4Angel<b> F\u00b4elix Gallardo</b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "<b>This author was held in Pentonville Prison after escaping internment in Le Vernet as an undesirable alien just before the fall of France, an experience he described in his memoir</b> <b>(+)</b> <em><b>The Scum of the Earth</b></em><b>. This author wrote about his experience imprisoned in Seville</b> <b>during the</b><em><b> Spanish Civil War in Dialogue with Death</b></em><b>. In this author\u2019s most famous work, the main character\u2019s guilty conscience is represented by toothaches as he reflects on how he betrayed his mistress and secretary (*)</b> Arlova and the Belgian Little Loewy. For the points, what British-Hungarian author criticised totalitarianism in his novel about Rubashov\u2019s imprisonment and execution,<em> Darkness at Noon</em>?", "answer": "Arthur<b> Koestler</b>", "metadata": "Literature - European Literature - Long Fiction"}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "A journey to this city known as its\u201cHumiliation\u201d started from Speyer and ended in a fortress in this city owned by (*)</b> Matilda of Tuscany. The most famous visitor to this city fasted for three days outside its castle during a blizzard to beg for forgiveness from Pope Gregory VII. For the points, Holy Roman Emperor Henry IV travelled to what Italian City to resolve the Lay Investiture Crisis?", "answer": "<b> Canossa</b> (accept<b> Canossa Castle</b>)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "<b>This man supposedly executed Juventinus and Maximinus after civilians ignored orders</b> <b>to keep those men in isolation. This man was speared at the Battle of (+)</b> <b>Samarra in a</b> <b>campaign against the Sassanids. Fireballs possibly caused by sabotage and an earthquake thwarted this man\u2019s attempt to build the Third Temple in Jerusalem. This man criticized the dangers of (*)</b> Christianity in his tract<em> Against the Galileans</em>, and he was his state\u2019s last non-Christian ruler after he succeeded Constantius. For the points, identify this Roman emperor who converted to paganism in 361, earning the name \u201cApostate.\u201d", "answer": "<b> Julian</b> the Apostate", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {"question": "<b>One member of this group had earlier founded the magazine</b><em><b> Liberation</b></em><b> and was David Dellinger. Thomas Foran helped prosecute this group though Lee Weiner and John Froines were acquitted. One defendant in this group poked fun of the fact that he and the judge shared the same last name by crying out (+) , \u201cDad, dad, have you forsaken me?!\u201d Charges against this group included considerations about violations of the Federal Communications Act and included (*)</b> Ramsey Clark discourage an indictment. One member of this group was bound and gagged in the court room and was Bobby Seale. Judge Hoffman was often insulted in, for the points, the trial of what group after the 1968 DNC protests?", "answer": "<b> Chicago Seven</b> (accept<b> Chicago Eight</b>)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "<b>Marie-Jeanne Lamartini\u00b4ere dressed in men\u2019s clothing and fought for this general\u2019s side at the Battle of Crete-a-Pierrot. This man called the Poles, \u201cthe White Negros of Europe\u201dand protected them after they joined his side. D\u00b4ed\u00b4ee (+) Bazile buried this man\u2019s mutilated body, who won the Battle of Vertieres over Donatien de Rochambeau. This man carried out an 1804 massacre but was overthrown by Alexander P\u00b4etion and Henri (*)</b> Chrisophe. Under this man, an island nation became the first to ban slavery in the Americas. For the points, name this emperor who succeeded Toussaint Louverture as leader of Haiti.", "answer": "Jean-Jacques<b> Dessalines</b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {"question": "<b>A militia of people who steal these items committed the Bor Massacre \u2013 that \u201cWhite Army\u201d was comprised of Lou Nouer who stole these in a ritualistic manner from Dinka rivals</b> <b>before being militarized by Riek (+)</b> <b>Machar. Fulani customs surrounding this property</b> <b>are driving ongoing conflict with the Adar, Tiv, and other Nigerian agriculturalists. One from of this good, the (*)</b> Watusi, a type of the form most common in Africa, the Sanga. Bride-price customs in northern Kenya are driving raids into Ethiopia to capture these animals. For the points, name these herd animals whose status as valuable property has driven civil wars throughout African history.", "answer": "<b> cow</b>s (accept equivalents like<b> cattle</b>;<b> kine;</b> prompt on \u201canimals\u201d or \u201cbovines\u201d or \u201cruminants\u201dor \u201cstock\u201d)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "<b>The cousin of the founder of this city founded Milwaukee, Wisconsin. The Treadwell Gold mine operated in this city. James Knox Taylor designed a governor\u2019s mansion in this</b> <b>city, which was almost replaced by a city named (+)</b> <b>Willow. This city included the St.</b> <b>Nicholas Russian Orthodox Church which was partially built by the (*)</b> Tlingit and it lies on the Gastineau Channel, across from Douglas Island. Replacing Sitka as capital, for the points, name this city isolated from much of Alaska.", "answer": "<b> Juneau</b>", "metadata": "Geography - Geography"}, {"question": "<b>One statue of this person was commissioned along with a statue of Isaiah by Nanni di Banco. In another statue of this person, a wing from a helmet stretches up this person\u2019s</b> <b>leg may symbolize (+)</b> <b>homosexuality. That bronze statue of this person was the first</b> <b>free-standing nude male sculpture since antiquity and was created by Donatello. A marble statue of this person, who symbolized Florence\u2019s resolve against its (*)</b> more powerful enemies, was commissioned for the roof of the Duomo and created by Michelangelo. For the points, name this Biblical person who killed Goliath.", "answer": "<b> David</b>", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Visual Fine Arts"}, {"question": "<b>During the American Revolution, Horatio Nelson led naval operations in this country on the HMS</b><em><b> Hichinbrook</b></em><b> in the 1780 San Juan Expedition. Carlist War veteran Charles Wilkins Webber helped Francisco Castell\u00b4on defeat the Legitimists in this country, who</b> <b>were opposed by (+)</b> <b>\u201cXatruch\u2019s Boys\u201d. After Cornelius Vanderbilt\u2019s Accessory Exchange</b> <b>Company\u2019s property in this country was seized by filibusterers, Vanderbilt sent secret agents to fight (*)</b> William Walker\u2019s republic in this nation. As a result of Mena\u2019s Rebellion, this country was occupied by U.S. troops who landed at Bluefields. The Bryan Chamorro treaty regarded a canal across, for the points, what Central American nation where the U.S. supported the Contras.", "answer": "<b> Nicaragua</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b>A subgroup of this company produced the \u201cBilofix\u201d product. Initially, Samsonite sold this company\u2019s products in the U.S. and Canada. Ai Weiwei used this company\u2019s products</b> <b>to create a medium to portray political activists. Hilary (+)</b> <b>Fisher Page\u2019s invention for</b> <b>Kiddicraft helped inspire this company\u2019s products, which was founded by Ole Kirk (*) </b>Christiansen. This company\u2019s name means \u201cI assemble\u201d in Latin and in Danish means \u201cPlay Well.\u201d For the points, name this toy company which makes interlocking plastic blocks.", "answer": "<b> Lego</b>", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Other Fine Arts - Architecture"}, {"question": "<b>This city\u2019s only dominion was over Burtscheid, and it even deployed soldiers to prevent Burtscheid from building roads into lands of the Duke of Julich. France was guaranteed conquests in Flanders after the War of the (+) Devolution by a treaty named for this city; Louis XIV would take advantage of that provision in this treaty along with the Peace of Nijmegen. In 1748, a treaty in this city led to celebrations that George II held with Handel\u2019s (*)</b><em> Music for the Royal Fireworks</em>. That treaty named for this city gave up Silesia to Frederick the Great and ended the War of the Austrian Succession. Charlemagne ruled his empire from, for the points, what German city also known as Aix-la-Chapelle?", "answer": "<b> Aachen</b> (accept<b> Bad Aachen</b> or<b> Aix-la-Chapelle</b> before mentioned)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "<b>One side in this battle refused to open negotiations because the letter addressed their leader as Esquire rather than any military title. During this battle, a surrounded Lord (+) Stirling broke through British lines so he could surrender to Leopold von Heister\u2019s Hessian troops instead. In this battle, the \u201cMaryland 400\u201d repeatedly attacked the Vecthe-Cortelyou House despite being outnumbered 7 to 1 resulting in less than two dozen making it back across (*)</b> Gowanus Creek. This battle was preceded by forces under William Howe landing at Gravesend Bay. George Washington led a night retreat to Manhattan at the conclusion of, for the points, what August 1776 battle in which British forces began their assault on New York City?", "answer": "Battle of<b> Long Island</b> (accept Battle of<b> Brooklyn</b> Heights)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "<b>A kosher variant of this food was named Loof. During WWII, the USO went on a tour named for this food. Ken (+) Daigneau gave the name for this food item. Nikita Khruschev claimed that without this food, \u201cwe wouldn\u2019t have been able to feed our army,\u201d while Margaret Thatcher claimed it was a \u201cwartime delicacy.\u201d Japanese Americans in Hawaii helped create a type of (*) </b> musubi with this food item. In the U.S. Army, this food was known as\u201cSpecial Army Meat.\u201d Made by Hormel Foods, for the points, name this pork luncheon meat.", "answer": "<b> SPAM</b> (90) <b>(+) a (*)</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}], "bonuses": []}